A Guide to the John R. Hutcheson Family Collection, 1890-1969
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
John R. Hutcheson Family Collection, 1890-1969 (Bulk, 1930-1950)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2015-001
1.7 cubic feet
Correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, and other items document the career and family of John R. Hutcheson. After earning his B.S. and M.S. degrees from Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VPI), John Redd Hutcheson (1886-1962) began working at the Virginia Agricultural Extension Service in 1914, becoming its director in 1919. Hutcheson was elected as president of VPI in 1945, serving until his nomination as VPI's first chancellor in 1947. The next year he became the first president of the VPI Educational Foundation, Inc. Hutcheson married Eleanor Parrott, with whom he had three children: Eleanor Catlett, John Hutcheson, Jr., and Robert Hutcheson.
John R. Hutcheson family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The John R. Hutcheson Family Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2014.
Biographical Note
One of seven children, John Redd Hutcheson (1886-1962) was born to Robert Francis and Mary Claiborne (née Barksdale) Hutcheson near Charlotte Courthouse, Virginia, on January 13, 1886. Dr. Jack, as he was affectionately known, married Eleanor Parrott in 1917, and the couple had three children: Eleanor Barksdale (Mrs. Charles, III) Catlett, John Redd Hutcheson, Jr., and Robert Parrott Hutcheson, who died serving during World War II. Hutcheson served briefly during World War I, and he operated the Edgemont Farm with his brother T.B. Hutcheson.
John Hutcheson earned a B.S. degree in 1907 and M.S. in 1909 from Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VPI, now Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University or Virginia Tech) as well as honorary doctorates from Clemson College in 1937 and North Carolina State College in 1947. Following graduation from VPI, he taught and served as principal for schools in Virginia and Mississippi as well as lectured at the University of Virginia. In 1914, Hutcheson joined the Virginia Agricultural Extension Service (now the Virginia Cooperative Extension), becoming its director in 1919.
In 1945, Hutcheson succeeded Julian A. Burruss as VPI’s ninth president, serving until the Board of Visitors elected Hutcheson to become VPI’s first chancellor in 1947. The following year, the Board established the VPI Educational Foundation, Inc. (known today as the Virginia Tech Foundation, Inc.) and named Dr. Jack its first president. He left the chancellorship in 1956, while remaining the foundation’s president until his death on January 23, 1962.
Sources:
John R. Hutcheson Family Collection, Ms2015-001, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
Kinnear, Duncan Lyle. 1972. The First 100 Years: A History of Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Blacksburg: Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
Robertson, Jenkins Mikell. 1972. Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University Historical Data Book, Centennial Edition. Blacksburg: Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
Scope and Content
The John R. Hutcheson Family Collection, 1890-1969, documents Hutcheson’s family and his career at the Virginia Agriculture Extension Service (VAES, now Virginia Cooperative Extension) and Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VPI, now Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University or Virginia Tech). Comprising correspondence, newspaper clippings, printed materials, photographs, and a scrapbook, the collection is divided into two series, Series I: Personal Papers and Series II: Professional Papers. The first series contains biographical sketches of John R. Hutcheson, legal documents, and printed material regarding his death and VPI. Correspondence discusses his and his son’s war service, the Hutcheson and Barksdale genealogy, and his extended family. A scrapbook compiled by Eleanor P. Hutcheson covers family and local events, such as weddings, deaths, and faculty and staff appointments at the VAES and VPI. Photographs and a photograph album depict Hutcheson and his wife, friends and events at the university and in the local area, and Hutcheson’s 1907 VPI football team.
The second series of Professional Papers is divided into three subseries: Subseries A: Appointments and Nominations, Subseries B: Virginia Agriculture Extension Service (VAES), and Subseries C: Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VPI). Appointments and Nominations contains correspondence and newspaper clippings regarding possible appointments for Hutcheson in the federal government and banking firms, his rejections of these offers in order to stay on at VAES and VPI, and his service as chairman on the Radford Area Defense Council. The VAES subseries documents his work as director, including the celebrations surrounding his 25th anniversary and the successes of the county agents and home demonstration workers in the program during the Great Depression. The VPI series concerns Hutcheson’s appointment as president of the university and includes a report card from 1890, among other items.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by type of material and chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
John Redd Hutcheson Papers, RG 2/9, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. Finding aid: http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv00190.xml
Edgemont Farm Papers, Ms2003-022, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. Finding aid: http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv00104.xml
Index Terms
Persons:
Hutcheson, Eleanor Parrott; Hutcheson, John Redd, 1886-1962 -- Correspondence
Family Names:
John R. Hutcheson family
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); University History; Virginia Cooperative Extension Service; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - Biographical information, 1940, 1962, undated (Box-folder 1-1)
  - John and Eleanor Hutcheson World War I letters, 1918 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Hutcheson and Barksdale genealogy and correspondence, 1926-1955 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Hon. R. F. Hutcheson obituary, January 13, 1940 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - World War II documents and poem, 1944, undated (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Virginia Tech Alumni Association card for John R. Hutcheson, 1951 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Will and estate paper for John R. Hutcheson, August 3, 1956 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Newspaper articles and printed material regarding death of John R. Hutcheson, 1962 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Printed material, 1928-1963 (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Photographs, [circa 1930s-1950s] (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Photograph album, [circa 1900s-1920s] (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Class of 1907 Senior Football Team photograph showing John R. Hutcheson in 2nd row, 3rd from right, 1907 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Scrapbook, Kith and Kin of Eleanor Parrott Hutcheson, January 1939 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Loose publications and newspaper clippings removed from scrapbook, 1939-1969 (Box-folder 2-3 to 2-5)
  - Loose photographs removed from scrapbook, 1941, undated (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Loose printed material removed from scrapbook, 1939-1948 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Loose correspondence removed from scrapbook, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 1-14 to 1-15)
- Series II: Professional Papers
  - Subseries A: Appointments and Nominations
    - John R. Hutcheson’s appointments, nominations, and personnel correspondence and newspaper clippings, 1917, 1929-1936 (Box-folder 1-16)
    - Radford Area Defense Council, 1941 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Subseries B: Virginia Agricultural Extension Service
    - Newspaper clippings and printed material regarding John R. Hutcheson, 1937-1944 (Box-folder 1-18)
    - 25th Anniversary for John R. Hutcheson as director, 1944 (Box-folder 1-19)
    - Correspondence, newspaper clippings, printed material, 1930-1945 (Box-folder 1-20 to 1-22)
    - Correspondence, primarily regarding county agents and home demonstration workers, 1932-1949 (Bulk, 1932-1934) (Box-folder 1-23 to 1-24)
  - Subseries C: Virginia Polytechnic Institute
    - Newspaper clippings and printed material regarding presidency of John R. Hutcheson, 1945 (Box-folder 1-25)
    - Audit of furniture at President's House, July 25, 1947 (Box-folder 1-26)
    - The Radford Review with letter from Mrs. Reagan Wyatt, 1952 (Box-folder 1-27)
    - Letter to Mrs. John R. Hutcheson with 1890 Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College report card, 1890, 1963 (Box-folder 1-28)